（左近）お待ちしておりました
サスケさん。
We were waiting for you, Sasuke.
里を抜けられたときをもって
あなたは→
It had already been decided that
you would be our leader
私どもの頭になることが
決まっておりました。
the moment you left the village.
（左近）今までのご無礼を
お許しください。
Please forgive
our rudeness up to now.
I don't care about any of that.
（サスケ）そんなことは
どうだっていい。
いくぞ。
Let's go!
始まりだ！
This is the beginning!
（シカマル）ナルト！　おい　ナルト！
Naruto! Hey, Naruto!
（ナルト）シカマル？
Shikamaru?
Sasuke's left the village.
（シカマル）サスケが里を抜けた。
大蛇丸のところへ向かってる。
He's headed for Orochimaru's.
なに！？　ウソだろ？
What?! You're lying right?
大蛇丸の手の者が　サスケを
手引きしている可能性が高い。
There is a strong possibility
that those under Orochimaru
are guiding Sasuke.
連れ戻すのが　任務だ。
Our mission is to bring him back.
Give me a minute!
I'll change right away!
ちょっと待ってろ！
すぐ　着替えっから。
（シカマル）とりあえず
５人と１匹　揃ったな。
Well, there are five of us,
and a dog.
しゃ～！　早速　行くってばよ。
All right! Let's get going!
その前に
いちばん大切なこと　言っとく。
Before that, I want to tell you
the most important thing.
サスケは　俺にとっちゃ→
Sasuke and I aren't close friends.
深いダチってわけでもねえし
別に　好きなヤツでもねえ。
In fact, I don't particularly like him.
However, he is also a shinobi from
the Village Hidden in the Leaves.
けど　サスケは同じ木ノ葉隠れの忍だ。
仲間だ。
He is a comrade!
Therefore, I will put my life
on the line to help him!
だから　命がけで助ける。
これが　木ノ葉流だ。
That's the way of the Leaf Village.
サスケは　俺にとって　大事な友達だ。
To me, Sasuke is a dear friend.
同じ第７班にいたからじゃない。
And it's not because
we were together on Team 7.
Even before that, I...
もっと前から…
ずっと前から　俺は…。
Sasuke's been our friend
from way back.
（チョウジ）サスケは
ずっと前から　僕たちの仲間だよ。
Yeah... After all, we were
in the same class.
（キバ）おう…　まぁ　同期だしな。
（ネジ）サスケの力は俺も認めている。
敵の手に渡すつもりなどない。
I'm certain of one thing:
Sasuke's got talent.
And I'm not going to let
the enemy take him away.
みんな！
Everyone!
よっしゃ！
ぜってぇ　連れ戻すってばよ。
Alll right! Let's get him back,
no matter what!
よし
じゃあ　フォーメーションの説明に入る。
Okay then.
I'll explain the formation.
待ってろよ　サスケ！
俺たちで　お前を助けてやる。
Just you wait, Sasuke.
We're gonna rescue you!
Sasuke, Lord Orochimaru has
given us one important task.
（左近）サスケ様…　実は
大蛇丸様から　おおせつかった→
大切なことが　ひとつ　あります。
あなたに　一度
死んでもらわなきゃなりません。
It will be necessary for you
to die once.
Die once, you said?
一度　死ぬだと？
醒心丸　これを飲んでもらいます。
Mind Awakening Pills.
Please take these.
死んで　そのあとは　どうなる？
And after I die?
You don't need to worry.
心配いりませんよ。
そのために　我々がいるのです。
That is why we are here.
我々の結界忍術で
副作用を抑えこみ→
We will use our Barrier Ninjutsu
to suppress the side effects,
to ease you away from eternal death
into a state of suspended animation.
永久の死から仮死状態へと
段階を和らげる。
No matter what happens,
I cannot afford to die yet.
《俺は　まだ　どうあっても
死ぬわけにはいかない》
頼むぞ。
I'm in your hands...
うぅ…。
（左近たち）四黒霧陣！
– Four Black Mists Formation!
封黒法印！
Black Seal!
All right, we're done with
the first part.
よし　ひと段落だぜ。
う…　うぅ…。
((イタチ：お前は弱い))
You are weak.
クソ…。
D-Damn it!
it's infinite, it's infinite, it's infinite, rock assault
eien desu eien desu eien desu totsugeki rock
I was asleep all this time, I kept quiet all this time
zutto nemutteta zutto damatteta
hey, it's calling us, hey, let's go
ooi yonde iru ooi itte mi yo
I can see something far away
tooku ni nanika ga mieru
something more important now than studying
benkyou yori mo ima taisetsu na mono
hey, it's calling us, hey, let's go
ooi yonde iru ooi itte mi yo
I think we can find it
mitsukarisou nanda
it's infinite, it's infinite, it's infinite, rock assault
eien desu eien desu eien desu totsugeki rock
see, you can overtake the future
mirai wa hora oinuite
this ship can really fly through the sky
hontou wa sora toberu fune
10th Anniversary 4-Episode Special
Parting
サスケーッ！
Sasuke!
俺から逃げんのか！
Are you running away from me?!
よう…　ウスラトンカチ。
Hey loser...
もう　俺にかまうな。
Don't concern yourself
with me anymore.
サスケ…。
Sasuke...
クックック…　なんだ　そのツラは。
What's with that look?
なんで…　なんでだよ　サスケ！
Why...?
Tell me why, Sasuke!
なんで　そんなふうに
なっちまったんだよ　お前は！
Why did you turn out like this?!
俺がどうなろうが
お前になんの関係がある！？
What I've become is
none of your business!
俺には俺の道がある。
I walk my own path.
たとえ　誰であろうと
指図される義理はねえ。
And I'm not obligated
to listen to anyone,
no matter who it is!
義理は…　ねえ？
"Not obligated"?
はっきり言ってやらぁ
お前ら　木ノ葉の連中と→
Let me make it clear!
I'm done fooling around with
you guys from the Hidden Leaf.
じゃれあうのは　もう終わりだ。
帰れ！
So go home!
チョウジ　ネジ　キバ　シカマル　ゲジマユ…　みんな
命がけでお前を追ってきたんだぞ。
Choji... Neji... Kiba...
Shikamaru... Bushy Brows...
We all put our lives on the line
to come after you.
ご苦労なこったな。
You wasted your time!
みんな…
みんな　お前のために戦って…。
What did you say?!
Everyone fought for your sake!
《チョウジ！》
Choji...
((僕だ！　コイツは僕がやる。
He's mine!
I will take care of him!
チョウジ…　お前　まさか！
Choji, you're not going to...?
シカマル　みんなを連れて　早く行って。
Shikamaru, take everyone and go!
何言ってんだ！　お前が一人で
やれる相手じゃねえってばよ！
What are you saying?!
He's not the kind of guy
you can handle on your own!
僕たちは
なんのために集まったんだ？
Why did we all come together
on this mission?
もし　このまま　サスケを見失えば
僕たちは　アイツの言うとおり→
If we lose track of Sasuke now,
we'll end up like he said...
バカな隊長と
ただのカスどもになっちゃうぞ！
A stupid captain and his losers.
チョウジ　絶対　あとから追いつけよ！
うん。
Choji, you better catch up
with us later.
Yeah.
みんな　行くぞ！
Let's go, everyone!
（次郎坊）フン！
お前をさっさと片づけて→
I'm going to get rid
of you quick,
アイツらも片づける！
and get rid of those guys too!
チョウジ！
Choji!
(みんな　行け～っ！))
Go, everyone!
《ネジ！》
Neji...
((行け！　俺がやる。
Go! I'll take care of this.
（赤丸）クゥーン…。
どうやら　アイツは
さっきのデブより強いらしいぜ。
Apparently this guy's stronger
than the fatso before.
それも　かなりな。
一人一殺の覚悟でいかないと→
And a whole lot more.
If we're not prepared to proceed
with "one kill per person,"
then our plan's not going
to work out.
計算が合わない。　そう話したな？
あぁ　そのとおりだ。
That's what we talked
about earlier right?
Yeah, that's right.
それに　こんなところで
止まっていては→
Plus, we won't be able to
catch up with Sasuke
サスケに追いつけなくなる。
if we stall here.
Naruto.
ナルト…　お前は
俺より　いい眼を持っている。
Your eyes are better than mine.
サスケは今　闇の中にいる。
Sasuke is now in the darkness.
行け！　俺もあとで追いつく。
うん！
Hurry up and go!
I'll catch up with you!
Gotcha!
よし　行くぜ！
Okay! Let's go!
You and Choji better catch up
with us later!
チョウジと一緒に　必ず追いつけよ！
ワン！
（鬼童丸）逃がすか！
Think I'm gonna let them get away?!
(はっ！))
《キバ！　シカマル！》
Kiba, Shikamaru...
Here you go!
((そらよ！
ナイスだってばよ　キバ　シカマル！
Nice! Kiba! Shikamaru!
計算どおりだ。
Just as calculated!
Punks!
（多由也）野郎…！
カスどもが　ナメた真似を！
You trash! Messing around with us.
ナルト　シカマル！　さっさと　ずらかるぜ。
Naruto! Shikamaru!
Let's get out of here!
逃がすか！
I won't let you get away!
They're faster than I expected.
思ったより　速ぇ！　赤丸！
ワン　ワン！
Akamaru!
仕掛けたら　早く来い！
Come quick after
you've set the bombs!
Don't you bark at me, you mutt!
ワン　じゃねえぞ　犬っころが！
赤丸！
Akamaru!
うわ～っ！
キバ！　赤丸！
チクショウ！
Kiba! Akamaru!
Damn it...
クソども～っ！
You punks!
しかたねえ…
俺が　どうにかすっから→
We have no choice.
I'll take care of this,
ナルト　お前は
棺桶　持って先　行け。
so you take the coffin
and go on ahead!
シカマル…。
早く行け！
Shikamaru...
Get going already!
（多由也）君麻呂！？
Kimimaro?!
（君麻呂）遅すぎるよ　多由也。
You were taking too long, Tayuya.
どうして　お前が…。
Why are you...?
今なら少しわかる。
I understand this feeling
a bit more now...
肉体という牢獄から抜け出した
情報生命としての感覚。
of being information-carrying energy
that has escaped
the prison of human flesh.
大蛇丸様の夢の一端に
触れている感覚。
The feeling of experiencing
a taste of Lord Orochimaru's dream.
《大蛇丸！？》
Orochimaru!
（君麻呂）この器は　大切な夢の器。
This vessel is an important vessel
for his dream.
なに　訳わかんねえこと
言ってんだ！　サスケを返せ！！
You jerk! Quit babbling nonsense!
Give Sasuke back!
うわっ！
あそこのゴミ２匹　頼みましたよ。
I leave those two pieces
of garbage to you.
ナルト　お前は
あの君麻呂ってヤツを追え。
Naruto, you go after Kimimaro.
シカマル…。
Shikamaru?
(ここは　俺が何とかする))
I'll take care of things here.
《ゲジマユ…》
Bushy Brows...
((そろそろだ。
It's about time...
待ちわびた…　大蛇丸様の野望。
I've waited so long.
The first step...
in Lord Orochimaru's ambition...
その第一歩だ。
サスケ…。
Sasuke...
Sasuke! What're you doing
with these guys?!
サスケ！　こんなヤツらと
何やってんだよ！
おら！　さっさと帰んぜ！
Come on! We're going home!
ククククク…。
ハハハハハハ…。
サスケ！　なあ
俺の声　聞こえてんだろうがよ！
Sasuke...
You can hear
my voice, can't you?!
待てよ　サスケ！
Wait, Sasuke!
It's futile.
ムダ…　死ね。
Die.
（リー）木ノ葉旋風！
Leaf Hurricane...
誰だ？
Who are you?
蘇りしは　木ノ葉の
美しき青き野獣　ロック・リーだ！
Leaf Village's Blue Beast resurrected!
Rock Lee!
ゲジマユ？　お前…　なんで…。
Bushy Brows? How did you...?
（リー）そんなことより
ナルト君は　サスケ君を。
More importantly, Naruto,
go get Sasuke!
(この人の相手は
僕に任せてください))
Please leave this person to me!
みんな…
みんな　お前を仲間だと言って…。
Everyone... everyone calls you
a friend and...!
サスケ！！
Sasuke!
お前は　仲間を何だと思ってんだ！！
What do you consider your comrades?!
ちっとは目が覚めたかよ？
Wake up already!
ああ…
目なら　とっくに覚めている。
I woke up a long time ago...
仲間とつるんで平和ボケした
お前らとの未来を夢見る→
from my stupidity that dreamed
about a peaceful future
together with my comrades.
バカな俺からな。
その仲間とやらと一緒にいて
俺は　強くなれたのかよ？
Did you think I'd get stronger
staying with comrades like that?
だから　里を出た。
That's why I left the village and
why I'm going to Orochimaru.
俺は　大蛇丸のところへ行く。
アイツは　お前の体を入れ物として
欲しがってるんだぞ！
He just wants your body for a vessel!
うっ…。
そんなことは　どうでもいい。
That doesn't matter to me.
俺の夢は　未来になんかない。
My dream is not in the future!
俺の夢は　過去…　そこにしかない。
My dream is in the past.
That's the only place it exists.
ナルト…　お前には
わかるはずもない。
Naruto... You can't possibly understand.
俺の夢は　肉親への復讐だ。
I dream of exacting revenge
against my own kin.
((イタチ：お前は俺と同じ
万華鏡写輪眼を開眼しうるものだ。
You are someone
who could be able
to use Mangekyo Sharingan
just like me.
ただし　それには条件がある。
However, on one condition...
(最も親しい友を殺すことだ))
You must kill...
your closest friend...
《イタチ　アンタを殺すためなら→
Itachi, if it's to kill you,
この先がどんな闇だろうと
俺は突き進む。
I will forge ahead,
no matter how dark the path.
どんなことがあっても
力を手に入れる》
No matter what happens,
I will obtain power.
《ネジ　お前の言ったとおりだ。
Neji, it's just like you said.
アイツは今　闇ん中にいるみてえだ》
it looks like he's in the depths
of darkness right now.
本気でくれやがって　チクショウ！
He really hit me at full power!
Damn it!
ああ　本気だ　殺すつもりでやった。
Yeah, I meant to kill you.
もう　俺ってば　お前にとって
仲間でもなんでもねえのかよ。
Don't you consider me
your comrade any longer?!
俺たち
第７班でやってきたことは全部→
Don't all those things
we did together on Team 7
何の意味もなかったのかよ！
mean anything to you?!
いや　無意味じゃない。
It wasn't meaningless...
俺にとってお前は
最も親しい友になった。
To me, you've become
my closest friend.
だったら　何で！
Then why...?
だからこそ
お前には殺す価値がある。
All the more reason why
there's meaning in
taking you down!
何だかわかんねえけど→
I don't fully understand,
俺を殺そうってのは
本気みてえだな　サスケよ。
but I guess you're trying to
take me down for real, Sasuke!
♪～
千鳥！
Chidori!
影分身の術。
Shadow Clone Jutsu!
螺旋丸！
Rasengan!
《あのサスケが友と言った　この俺に。
Sasuke actually came out
and said that I'm his friend.
だから
この螺旋丸で確かめたいんだ》
And that's exactly
the reason why
I wanted to verify it
using this Rasengan.
《チクショウ　俺のフルパワーの千鳥を…。
Damn it!
That loser was able to counter
あの落ちこぼれが》
my fully powered up Chidori
to that extent?!
《もう間違いねえじゃねえか。
There's no mistake about this.
お前は　本気で俺を…》
You really intend to kill me.
《平気で殺せちまうのかよ　サスケ》
You're really trying to
kill me, Sasuke.
《俺たちは友達じゃないのかよ》
I thought... we were friends.
《友達と思ってたのは
俺のほうだけかもしんねえ。
I might have been the only one
who thought that we were friends.
でも　しようがねえだろ》
It's too late now.
《万華鏡写輪眼…
最も親しい友を殺すこと》
Mangekyo Sharingan...
To kill my closest friend.
何だ　この赤いチャクラは。
What is this red chakra?
サスケ　お前は大蛇丸なんかにゃ
やらねえってばよ。
Sasuke! I'm not gonna let
Orochimaru take you away!
俺がお前の手足の
骨全部折ってでも止めてやらぁ！
I will stop you,
even if I have to break
every one of your limbs!
お前は　いったい何なんだ！
What the hell are you?!
友達だ！
Your friend!
いいかげん目覚ませ。
Come on! Wake up, already!
まだ覚めねえってんなら
ホントにバキバキにして→
If you don't come to your senses,
I'll break you so that
you can't move
動けねえようにして連れてくぞ！
and I'll take you home that way!
うるせえんだよ。
親も兄弟もいねえテメエに→
Shut up...
Why the hell do
you think you understand?
俺の何がわかるってんだよ。
You have no parents or siblings!
初めから独りっきりだったテメエに→
What makes you think that you can
understand anything about me?!
俺の何がわかるってんだ　あっ！
You've been alone from the start!
つながりがあるからこそ
苦しいんだ！
It's because I have the ties
that I feel this agony.
それを失うことが　どんなもんか
お前なんかに　わかってたまるか！
How could you
possibly understand
what it feels like to lose all that?!
ホントの親子や兄弟なんて
確かに俺にはわかんねえ。
It's true that I can't
understand how it feels
to really have parents or brothers...
けど　お前といるとき
兄弟ってこんな感じかなってよ。
But when I'm with you...
I wonder if having a brother
feels something like that.
何でだ　何でそこまでして　俺に…。
Why? Why is it that you go
to this extent for me?
俺にとっちゃ
やっとできたつながりなんだ。
For me, it's a bond that
I've finally been able to have!
だから　俺は
お前を止めるんだってばよ。
That's why I'm gonna stop you.
A bond...
つながりか…。
《そうだな　ナルト…
俺も最初から感じていた》
That's true, Naruto.
I felt it from the very beginning too.
こい　ナルト！
Come on, Naruto!
だったら　そのつながりを
俺は断ち切るまでだ！
In that case,
I just have to cut that bond!
断ち切るか…。
Cut it, huh?
だったら　なんで今更　額当てを。
Then why did you put on
your headband at this point?
認めてやるよ。　お前は強い。
I'll acknowledge you.
You're strong.
なぜなら　お前も俺と同じ
孤独の痛みを知る者だ。
And the reason is because
you're someone who knows
the pain of solitude like I do...
そして　その痛みが人を強くする。
and that pain makes people stronger.
だからこそ
このつながりを断つことで→
And for that very reason,
by cutting that bond,
俺は　更なる強さを手に入れる。
I will be able to obtain
even greater strength.
今からは対等に戦ってやる。
I will fight you now
on equal terms.
だが　お前は俺の額に傷ひとつ
つけることすら　できやしない。
However...
You won't even be able to
make a scratch on my forehead.
そのことに変わりはないがな。
That's something that
won't change in the least.
もう何言っても
無駄みてぇだな　サスケ。
It seems that whatever I say won't
have any effect anymore, huh, Sasuke?
おしゃべりは　もう終わりだ。
I'm done with talking.
ここからは　ただ　戦いだ。
From here on out, we only fight.
こい！
Come!
うぉ～！
急げ！
Hurry!
てやぁ～！
これは　まずいぞ！
This is bad!
医療班か！
まずは　コイツから頼む。
The Medical Corps!
Please tend to him first.
大丈夫か？
俺は平気だ。
Are you all right?
I'm okay.
Look after the others.
他のヤツを診てやってくれ。
ナルト君は
追いついたでしょうか？
I wonder if Naruto caught up to him?
（カカシ）間に合ってくれよ。
Please let me get there in time!
なぁ　ナルト　そろそろ
終いにしようぜ　この戦いを！
Hey Naruto, how about we bring
this fight to a close?
螺旋丸！
千鳥！
– Rasengan!
– Chidori!
♪～
ナルト　俺は…。
Naruto... I'm...
《復讐者なんだ…》
an avenger.
カカシ先生…。
Kakashi Sensei...
You're awake!
気づいたか？
Where's Sasuke?
サスケは…。
So he's gone.
行っちまったのか…。
サクラちゃん　ごめん…。
I'm sorry, Sakura.
（大蛇丸）待っていたわよ　サスケ君。
I've been waiting for you, Sasuke.
I'm glad you came.
よく来てくれたわね。
I want power.
俺に力を！
Yes, of course. Just follow me.
いいわよ　ついてきなさい。
Itachi...
《イタチ…　俺は俺のやり方で
力を手に入れる。
I will get my hands on power,
by my own way!
俺のやり方でアンタを超える！》
I will surpass you, my own way!
俺は　ぜってぇ諦めねえ　サスケ。
I'll never give up on you, Sasuke.
俺と　お前は友達だ。
We're friends.
これからも　ずっと…　ずっと。
Now and forever...
you and I held hands tightly and a light was born
kimi to boku nigirishimeta futatsu no te no naka de
let's release it now
umareta hikari ima hanatou
the town, tinged amber by the sunset
kohaku iro no yuuyake ni somerareta
projects a sad light and shadow
machi wa kanashii hikari to kage utsushite ita
I've encountered and gotten tangled
ikutsu mono kiseki no ito
in so many miraculous threads
tsunagatte karamatte tadoritsuita yo
it all starts here and now
hajimeru no wa ima kono basho kara
it'll clear up after the rain, become that cloud
ame nochi hare ano kumo ni nare
and swim towards the present
ima wo oyoi de yuku
toss away the hesitation
sono kokoro shibaritsuketeru
that clings to your heart
tamerai furihodoite
you and I held hands
kimi to boku nigirishimeta
and deep inside
futatsu no te no naka de
is the eternal proof of you
kieru koto nai kimi no akashi
with our liberated hands
jiyuu na sono ryoute de
let's start again, from here
koko kara mata hajimeyou
Next Episode
The Akatsuki army led by Madara
with their Reanimated Shinobi and White Zetsu troops number 100,000.
皆様　お変わりございませんか？
The opposing army with Gaara leading the Allied Shinobi Forces
美空ひばりです。
comprised of the Five Hidden Villages and the samurai,
では　最後まで　ごゆっくり→
number 80,000.
お楽しみください。
The Fourth Great War is about to begin.
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "For My Friend"
（宮本）『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！　にっぽんの歌』。
For My Friend
I want to protect Naruto!
（松丸）今回は　ご覧の
豪華歌手の皆さんによる→
Tune in again!